Guide to the Rencher Nicholas Harris Papers, 1851-1980 and undated, bulk 1926-1965
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Rencher Nicholas Harris papers 1851-1980 and undated, bulk 1926-1965
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Harris, Rencher Nicholas, 1900-1965.
16.5 linear feet Extent: 2,112 Items
African American civic leader during the period following the Brown decision of 1954 and the Civil Rights Movement. Harris was the first African American city councilman in Durham, N.C., and the first black man to sit on the Durham County Board of Education. The Rencher Nicholas Harris Papers span the years from 1851 to 1980, with the bulk dating from 1926 to 1965. The collection consists mainly of clippings, correspondence, legal papers, photographs, printed materials, journals and diaries, scrapbooks, oversize maps, and reports relating to Harris' work in political and educational affairs in Durham, North Carolina in the 1950s and early 1960s as a member of the City Council and the School Board, with emphasis on school desegregation, civil rights, and race relations in Durham. Also represented is Harris' business career in banking, insurance, and real estate, his role as an official of the Bankers' Fire Insurance Company, and his civic activities, including leadership roles in the NAACP, Lincoln Hospital, and North Carolina Mutual Insurance, and Mechanics and Farmers Bank, all serving African Americans in Durham. Some biographical materials, family papers, and correspondence also relate to his wife, Plassie Williams Harris. Part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture at Duke University.
RL.00515
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Rencher Nicholas Harris Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1966.
Biographical Note
Chronology List
1900, October 7 Born in Abingdon, Virginia
1917 Graduated from Corey Memorial Institute in Portsmouth, Virginia
1917-1918 Attended Virginia Union University of Richmond
1919-1920 Attended Northwestern University School of Commerce
1921 First employed by Banker's Fire Insurance Company
1922 Married Plassie Williams of Durham, North Carolina
1935 Appointed as Vice-Secretary of Banker's Fire Insurance Company
1949 Ran for Durham City Council and was defeated
1953 Elected to Durham City Council
1957 Declined to run for a second term to City Council
1958 Accepted appointment to fill an unexpired term on the Durham School Board
1959 Reappointment for four-year term on School Board
1962 Resigned from School Board due to ill health
1965, January 4 Died in Durham, N.C.
Collection Overview
The Rencher Nicholas Harris Papers span the years from 1851 to 1980, with the bulk dating from 1926 to 1965. The collection consists mainly of clippings, correspondence, legal papers, photographs, printed materials, journals and diaries, scrapbooks, and reports relating to Harris' work in political and educational affairs in Durham, North Carolina in the 1950s and early 1960s as a member of the City Council and the School Board, with emphasis on school desegregation, civil rights, and race relations in Durham. Also represented is Harris' business career in banking, insurance, and real estate, his role as an official of the Bankers' Fire Insurance Company, and his civic activities, including leadership roles in the NAACP, Lincoln Hospital, and North Carolina Mutual Insurance, all in Durham. Some biographical materials and correspondence also relate to his wife, Plassie Williams Harris. In detailing the business and government official activities of Durham's first African American city councilman, the first black man to sit on the Durham County Board of Education, and an active, if rather moderate, African American civic leader during the period following the Brown decision of 1954 and the Civil Rights Movement, this collection is especially significant for the documentation it offers on the problems of city government and race relations in the mid-twentieth-century South. Includes a large group of oversize maps of Durham, N.C. Part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture at Duke University.
Collection Arrangement
The collection is arranged in twelve series, of which Volumes and Scrapbooks and Durham City Council are the largest. The much smaller groupings are: Clippings; Correspondence; Genealogy and Biography; Insurance and Banking; Legal Papers; Miscellany; North Carolina College; Photographs; Printed Materials; and Speeches. There is also a group of oversize materials that were separated from the main collection and rehoused.
Subject Headings
Harris, Rencher Nicholas, 1900-1965; Harris, Plassie Williams; Bankers' Fire Insurance Company -- Employees; Lincoln Hospital (Durham, N.C.); Mechanics and Farmers Bank (Durham, N.C.); National Association for the Advancement of Colored People -- Durham Branch (Durham, N.C.); North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company (Durham, N.C.); African American businesspeople -- North Carolina -- Durham; African American politicians -- North Carolina -- Durham; African Americans -- Economic conditions -- North Carolina; African Americans -- North Carolina -- Durham -- History; African Americans -- North Carolina -- Durham -- Social conditions; Banks and banking -- North Carolina -- Durham; Civil rights movements -- Southern States; Education -- North Carolina -- Durham; Insurance companies -- North Carolina -- Durham; Municipal governance -- North Carolina -- Records and correspondence; Public schools -- Durham (N.C.) -- History; Race relations -- Political aspects; Real estate business -- North Carolina -- Durham; School integration -- North Carolina -- Durham; School integration -- United States; Durham (N.C.) -- Commerce; Durham (N.C.) -- History; Durham (N.C.) -- Politics and government; Durham (N.C.) -- Race relations; Diaries; Journals; Maps; Scrapbooks
Related Material
The Harward and Howard collections focus on Durham N.C. race relations, school segregation and integration, and Durham city politicas and government from the 1960s-1980s. The Lincoln Hospital and N.C. Mutual collections are included here due to R.N. Harris' involvement with both entities, as well as the material located within the Harris collection relating to the two former collections.
Stephen C. Harward Papers, 1949-1975 and undated, bulk 1963-1975
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Chris D. Howard Papers, 1972-1983
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Lincoln Hospital (Durham, N.C.) Records, 1901-1998 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company Archives, 1850-2008 and undated, bulk 1898-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- Clippings Series, 1951-1966, 1980 and undated, (1 folder)
  Contains newspapers, newsletter clippings, some oversize, pertaining to activities of and topics of concern for Rencher Nicholas Harris and his wife, Plassie Williams Harris, and associated items such as correspondence and election materials, particularly referring to voting as related to race.
  - Clippings, 1951-1966 and undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence Series, 1920-1965 and undated, (3 boxes)
  Comprised of letters, telegrams, and other types of correspondence, in the form of personal exchanges between Harris and his wife and family; letters dealing with his campaign and election to the Durham city Council in 1953; and correspondence touching on his business activities. Of particular note are letters written to Harris from Carla Myerson (later Eugster) during her stay in England in 1951, which are filled with observations and impressions about England and its contrasts to America, especially on race relations. Starting in the mid-1950s, letters Harris received from Durham citizens give evidence of the effects of the Brown decision; some letters, for example, call his attention to segregation in airports and ballparks. The issue of public school desegregation comes to the fore beginning about 1959. Dispersed among the correspondence are clippings, financial or business documents, photographs, and publications, often attached to the correspondence with which they are associated. The series is arranged in chronological order.
  - Letters, 1920-1939 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1950-1951 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Includes a Survey of the Negro Vote in the 1952 Presidential Election compiled and distributed by the NAACP.
  - Letters, 1953 Jan.- May (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters, 1953 Jun.- Dec. (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Includes reproduction of painting of R. N. Harris for calendar art.
  - Letters, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Letters, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Letters, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Letters, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Letters, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Letters, 1965 and undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Durham City Council Series, 1946-1964 and undated, (10 boxes)
  Comprised of materials concerning Harris' term on the Durham City Council and his service on various committees. The material takes the form of clippings, correspondence, personal notes, and committee documents, including financial papers, maps, meeting agendas and minutes, newsletters and pamphlets, policy statements, proposals, and reports. Materials in three boxes concern Harris' service on the Durham Board of Education, ranging from audit reports of cafeteria systems and book funds to denials to requests for school integration. In addition, there are several subseries that touch on the activities of the Committee on Human Relations, Lincoln Hospital, and the Durham NAACP (for which Harris served as president). The NAACP subseries include an undated "Manual for Workers in NAACP Membership Campaigns," and correspondence and clippings pertaining to the NAACP and its projects. The subseries are arranged in alphabetical order. Unless otherwise noted, each heading represents one folder of material. Some material has been removed to an oversize folder.
  - Airport, 1946, 1953-1956 and undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Assessments, 1954-1955, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Includes an existing land use map of the Hayti-Elizabeth Street Renewal Area from the Durham Redevelopment Commission, dated 1960 Jun.
  - Board of Education, 1957-1958 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Board of Education, 1959 and undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Board of Education: Durham City Schools Audit Report, 1960 Jun. 30 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Board of Education: Durham City Schools Audit Report - Activity funds, 1960 Jun. 30 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Board of Education: Durham City Schools Audit Report - Assorted funds, 1960 Jun. 30 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Board of Education: Durham City Schools Audit Report - Cafeteria system, 1960 Jun. 30 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Board of Education: Durham City Schools Audit Report - Activity funds, 1961 Jun. 30 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Board of Education: Durham City Schools Audit Report - Assorted funds, 1961 Jun. 30 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Board of Education: Durham City Schools Audit Report - Cafeteria system, 1961 Jun. 30 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Board of Education: Durham City Schools Audit Report - General fund, 1961 Jun. 30 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Board of Education: Durham City Schools Fallout shelter survey, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Board of Education: "An Analysis and Comparison of the Academic Adjustment and Problems of Probation Students and Honors Students at North Carolina College," 1952 Oct. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Board of Education: "Financial Support of Secondary Education for Negroes in Georgia," 1952 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Board of Education, 1960 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Includes summons in lawsuit against the Durham City Board of Education for maintaining segregated school systems.
  - Board of Education, 1961-1962 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Board of Education, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Industrial Education Center, 1958-1963 and undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Bonds, 1954-1960 and undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Budget Committee, 1952-1954 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Budget Committee 1954 and undated (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Budget Committee 1955 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Budget Committee 1956-1957 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - City Extension, 1953-1957 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Committee of 100 and DIDCO, 1954-1956 and undated (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Committee on Human Relations, 1956-1961 and undated (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Crain and Denbo Matter, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Fire Department, 1951-1956 and undated (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Government Center, 1947, 1953, 1956-1957 and undated (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Includes oversize maps of Durham and plans for Durham City and County lands.
  - Health Department, 1954 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Hospitalization Plans for City Employees, 1956 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Housing, 1954, 1955 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Joint Committee on Use of City-County Land, 1956-1957 and undated (Box 8, Folder 10)
    Includes preliminary plan for city-county lands, 1956 Dec. 6.
  - Lincoln Hospital, 1952-1964 and undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Maps, 1953-1963 and undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
    Includes various maps for Durham planning
  - NAACP (Durham Chapter), 1952-1955 and undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Various material relating to Durham and organizations therein, 1951, 1957, 1961 and undated (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Parking Meter Matters, 1953-1955 and undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Political Matters, 1944-1961 and undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Recreation Committee, 1953-1956 and undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Redevelopment Commission of Durham, 1961-1964 and undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Contains material regarding theยยHayti-Elizabeth StreetยยRedevelopment Project, including Preliminary Certificates of Title as well as Offers of Sale of Land [Map No. 39 of the Durham County Township Tax Maps removed to Oversize Materials.]
  - Safety Patrol, 1953, 1955, and undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - St. Titus Episcopal Church, 1950-1952, 1960-1964 and undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Street Committee, 1952-1956 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Taxi Cabs and Buses, 1952-1956 and undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Telephone Franchise and Rates, 1917, 1946-1955 and undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Traffic Committee, 1953-1956 and undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Water and Sewer Department, 1952-1957 and undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Youth Board and Juvenile Court, 1955-1956 and undated (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Zoning Ordinance, 1957 and undated (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Genealogy and Biography Series, 1943-1966 and undated, (1 folder)
  Includes a chronology for the life of Plassie Williams Harris, wife of Rencher Nicholas Harris, written in her own hand, and various lists of names and addresses kept by the Harrises.
  - Biographical chronology of Plassie Williams Harris and various addresses, names, 1943, 1948, 1966 and undated (Box 14, Folder 1)
- Insurance and Banking Series, 1952-1965 and undated, (4 folders)
  Comprised of materials pertaining to insurance or banking institutions with which Harris dealt. Materials from Durham's North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company occupy one folder and include correspondence, financial statements, and informational and advertising materials. The folder on "Assorted Companies" contains similar materials for a number of banking and insurance institutions, including American Equitable Assurance, Bankers' Fire and Casualty Insurance Company, Loyal Automobile Insurance Company, Mutual Savings and Loan Association, Southeastern Fidelity Fire Insurance Company, and Southern Fidelity Mutual Insurance Company. There are also ledgers, correspondence, financial documents, and reports pertaining to the Mechanics and Farmers Bank.
  - Assorted companies, 1952-1965 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company, 1952-1953, 1959-1964 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Mechanics and Farmers Bank, 1946, 1951, 1960-1965 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Mechanics and Farmers Bank deposit and check books, 1954-1961 and undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
- Legal Papers Series, 1951-1963 and undated, (2 folders)
  Includes documents related to the financial and legal matters between Harris, North Carolina Mutual Life Insurance Company, and Thomas A. Allen, as well as deeds and contracts, and some documents regarding school controversies.
  - Thomas A. Allen records, 1954-1959 and undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Legal papers, 1951-1963 and undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
- Miscellaneous Papers Series, 1952-1957 and undated, (1 folder)
  Comprised of a single folder containing a variety of materials including a list of names and addresses of Durham clergy, a 1952-1953 membership card for the General Alumni Association of Virginia Union University, a medal presented "by the citizens of Portsmouth, Va. for loyal service in the World War," and assorted other memorabilia and ephemera belonging to Harris.
  - Miscellaneous items, 1952-1957 and undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
- North Carolina College Series, 1952-1964 and undated, (1 folder)
  Comprised of materials documenting Harris' affiliations and service with the North Carolina College of Durham (later North Carolina Central University). The majority of these materials consists of correspondence and reports pertaining to college properties and properties adjacent to the college under review for acquisition by the college; included among these materials are associated maps and property and architectural photographs. Also included are materials pertaining to the 1955 Real Estate and Builders Conference that was held at and partially sponsored by the North Carolina College Commerce Department and at which Harris gave the key address.
  - North Carolina College materials, 1952-1964 and undated (Box 16)
- Photographs Series, 1954, 1956, 1960 and undated, (1 folder)
  Contains 14 photographs of Harris and/or his family or business associates. Most of the individuals in the photographs are identified, but few have dates associated with them. Plassie Williams Harris and J. S. Stewart are present in a number of the photographs.
  - Photographs, 1954, 1956, 1960 and undated (Box 16)
- Printed Materials Series, 1924, 1947, 1953-1965 and undated, (3 folders)
  Comprised of advertising and informational media, manuals, newsletters, pamphlets, postcards, programs, and other printed materials on a variety of topics. One folder contains approximately 30 publications mostly relating to race relations and school desegregation.
  - Printed materials, 1924, 1947, 1953-1965 and undated (Box 17)
- Speeches Series, 1953-1963 and undated, (2 folders)
  Contains clippings of source material, event programs, written notes, and scripts or note cards of speeches given by Harris. Also included are typescripts for two 1963 speeches given by the Dean of Duke Chapel James T. Cleland.
  - Speeches, 1953-1963 and undated (Box 18)
- Volumes and Scrapbooks Series, 1851-1964 and undated, bulk 1939-1964, (15 boxes)
  Comprised of bound volumes of personal and business documents relating to Harris. The series is divided into three subseries arranged alphabetically: Appraisals, Memoranda Books, and Scrapbooks and Volumes. The Appraisals group contains bound groupings of real estate appraisals done by Harris mainly in the Durham area from 1939 to 1964. The appraisal reports include many photographs of commercial and residential properties. The Memoranda subseries includes small volumes from 1945-1963, most of which contain little information. The 1955 volume, however, contains the text of several of Harris' speeches and a few newspaper clippings concerning his views on desegregation. The Scrapbooks and Albums subseries consists of a letterbook covering the years 1957-1962, dealing mainly with a testimonial dinner for Harris in 1957 and with his resignation from the School Board in 1962; a scrapbook containing clippings about Durham civic leaders and some snapshots from 1958; a folder of letters and expressions of sympathy to Mrs. Harris on the occasion of Harris' death in 1965; and the Harris family album that has in it family letters and documents as far back as 1851, quantities of clippings pertaining to Harris' political career, and many photographs.
  - Appraisals, (10 boxes) (Box 19-28)
  - Memoranda, (2 boxes) (Box 29-30)
  - Scrapbooks and Albums, (3 boxes) (Box 31-33)
- Oversize Materials, 1947-1980 and undated, (5 folders)
  Chiefly large maps of Durham city and county, used for municipal planning purposes, but also includes some clippings.
  - Clippings Series materials (Opaperfolder 1)
  - Durham Maps (Opaperfolder 2)
  - Durham Maps (Opaperfolder 3)
  - Durham Maps (Opaperfolder 4)
  - Durham Maps (Opaperfolder 5)